we will not talk about raid 3 because
it's very very rarely used today so we
will go to raid 4 which is actually not
very often used but it helps understand
how it works to understand how raid 5
which is more often used works raid 4
uses a technique called block
interleaved parity it uses n disks and
minus 1 all but one of these discs
contain data which is striped across
these disks just like in raid 0 and then
the last disk has the parity blocks that
protect all of the blocks of the N minus
one disks so let's look at an example
with four disks so we said that three of
the discs contain data so this would be
stripe zero then here we have stripe
three four and five and so on so we just
distribute our data across all but one
disk and then we take the date of stripe
zero X or the whole stripe bit by bit
with stripe one X or the whole thing
with stripe 2 and what we get will be as
long as a stripe and that gives us the
parity stripe for 0 1 & 2 and we put
that on the fourth disk then we go to
the next stripe on each disk XOR them
and that gives us the parity stripe for
these three stripes and so on so the
idea here is that if let's say one disk
fails we have the data of the two disks
here and we have the parity we can
reconstruct what was on the first disk
by exiting these three or if there is an
error in just for example this one
stripe gets too damaged to reconstruct
by using the error correction code of
this disk in that case again we can read
this stripe this stripe and the parity
and then reconstruct what should have
been the bits of this so effectively now
we can tolerate the failure of any one
disk but the cost is not two times as
many disks as we need to store the data
here for example we are paying only one
quarter of the whole system is spent
on parity and 3/4 on the data whereas
with mirroring we would have spent half
of the overall capacity of the system on
the mirroring you can think of rate for
as kind of a more general technique than
mirroring because in reality using two
discs for rate for it's very similar to
mirroring because here we will store the
bits of the data and here we will store
the same bits because a bit when you
don't exert it with anything you just
put it here so mirroring is just an
extreme case of raid 4 when n is just 2
but you want to go to more than two with
rate 4 because that allows you to have
lower cost while still being able to
recover from losing one disk so now what
does a write do it must write one of the
data discs and it must read and write
the parity disk to update the parity
because one of the stripes have changed
I read however only needs to read the
data from the disk where the data is
we will only reconstruct the data if
that read fails but in the normal
scenario where we get the data we want
we don't even have to consult the parity
bit for reads